Yu'er
玉児
Come let the empress see you
こっちに来て女王にあなたを見せなさい
How can this be?
どうしてこんなことがあり得るの
Right
そうだね
How can he not follow orders?
どうして命令に従わないことができるのか
Rashly attack
軽率に攻撃する
But he did win the battle after all
でも相手に勝ったことには変わりないじゃないか
Your Majesty arrives
陛下がお越しになる
Pay respects to Your Majesty
陛下にお目にかかります
Let's all speak
みんな話してごらん
What's the matter?
どうしたの
Your Majesty
陛下
I
しん
Wish to impeach Zhu Yuanzhi
朱元之を弾劾すべきだ
Not long ago
つい先日
Our Beishuo Army
我が北朔軍
Engaged in close combat with Wuzhao's Shixin division
鄔伖石信部と短刀で交戦する
The Ministry of War ordered General Zhu
兵部の詔令朱将軍
After repelling the enemy
敵を撃退した後
To withdraw and defend the base
駐屯地を守る
But General Zhu did not follow orders
可朱将軍は命令に従わなかった
Privately advanced recklessly
私が無鉄砲に行動する
Actually pursued deep into Wuzhao territory
まさか直接ウーウーの腹地まで迫るとは
Causing heavy losses to our troops
我が軍の兵馬に甚大な損害をもたらした
And disrupted Your Majesty's approved battle plan
さらに陛下が勅定された作戦方針も
Completely
全部めちゃくちゃにされた
But no matter what
どう言おうとも
General Zhu achieved a great victory this time
朱将軍は今回大勝を収めた
The entire southern Pingzhou
平州の南部全体
Was recovered by the Beishuo Army
すべて北朔軍によって奪還された
I think
私は思う
Not only should he not be punished
罰するべきではないどころか
But should be heavily rewarded
さらに大きな報酬を与えるべきだ
To encourage the enterprising spirit of all
天下の人々の進取の心を奨励するために
I remember
覚えています
The court only gave General Zhu
朝廷はただ朱将軍にだけ与えた
Supplies to repel the enemy
敵を退けるための糧秣
The money for his campaign
彼が戦争に出す兵隊のお金
Where did it come from?
どうやって来たのですか
This Zhu Yuanzhi
この朱元之
Is almost declaring himself king
彼はもう少しで独立して王を名乗るところだった
He uses
彼はくしゃみをしている
Your Majesty's land reform as a banner
彼は陛下の土地改革の旗印のもとに行動している
In Qingzhou
青州で
Extensively seized land
土地を大々的に収奪する
Directly distributed to the army
直接軍に分配する
But General Zhu
コシュ将軍
Did successfully implement Your Majesty's new policies
陛下の新政を概ね成功裏に推進したと言える
This is a great merit
これは大きな功績です
Forcibly seized from great families
大地主や富豪を強奪する
Privately divided court land
私が朝廷の土地を分ける
This
彼はこれ
Is clearly
これは明らかにです
Bandit behavior
山賊の行為
Alright, alright
はいはい
Stop arguing
もう騒がないで
Let's put this matter aside for now
この件はひとまず保留にしましょう
Discuss another day
また日を改めて話し合いましょう
Court dismissed
散朝さんちょう
This phoenix
この鳳の頭
Has gotten fat recently
最近太った
It seems
どうやら
Fan Zhong's meals are quite good
ファンチョンの食事はなかなかいいね
Let's talk
話してみて
About General Zhu's matter
朱将軍のこと
What do you think?
あなたたちはどう思いますか
Although General Zhu won a small victory
朱将軍は小さな勝利を収めたものの
He so flagrantly ignored court orders
しかし彼はこのように朝廷の命令を顧みなかった
If something major happens in the future
もし未来に大きな出来事が起こったら
And General Zhu still acts willfully
朱将軍はやはり一方的に行動する
Cannot coordinate closely with the center
中央と緊密に連携できない
This would be a catastrophic hole
これが天を傾ける穴だ
Your son believes
私は思います
We cannot have wishful thinking
甘い考えを持ってはいけない
Should be punished
それは罰せられるべきだ
A general in the field
外出中です
May not always follow the ruler's orders
君の命令には従わないことがある
The battlefield changes in an instant
戦場では一瞬一瞬で状況が変わる
If everything follows central orders
もしすべてが中央の指令に従うなら
Then how do we seize opportunities?
それなら何の戦闘機を捕まえるのか
Since ancient times
古くから
Victory and defeat are decided in an instant
勝負手はほんの一瞬の間に決まる
Father
父上
Your son believes
私は思います
General Zhu's intentions are correct
朱将軍の本心は正しいです
And he's brave and decisive
再び勇敢で果断
Should be rewarded
その賞
Xuan shall prosper
大いに宣伝して興るべし